<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ide | koraktor's $stdout]]></title>
  <link href="http://stdout.koraktor.de/blog/categories/ide/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stdout.koraktor.de/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-03T10:40:29+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://stdout.koraktor.de/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sebastian Staudt]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A word on IDEs]]></title>
    <link href="http://stdout.koraktor.de/blog/2010/08/11/a-word-on-ides/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://stdout.koraktor.de/blog/2010/08/11/a-word-on-ides</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What would be a good start for a blog about programming? I’ll start with IDEs.</p>

<p>I won’t start off a fanboy war here. That wouldn’t be a good start for my blog
I think. I just want to summarize my experiences with IDEs.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Let’s start with <a href="http://www.eclipse.org">Eclipse</a>. Anyone knows it, almost anyone has used it and
most of them still use it. Eclipse is for IDEs what Windows is for operating
systems – a quasi standard. To be honest I don’t like Eclipse. It’s a good IDE
for sure – lots of useful plugins, lots of configuration options and so on.
But it lacks real style – just like Windows ;). Even changing colors is a pain
in the a** and I don’t like coding with a white background. Another downside of
Eclipse for me is it’s pretty focused on Java development, although there are
lots of plugins that integrate new languages, but it just doesn’t feel right –
although there are other Eclipse-based IDEs like <a href="http://www.aptana.com/rails">RadRails</a> that have better
support for other languages. On a side note Eclipse has a guite good support
for Subversion, but when I switched to Git this bonus didn’t count anymore.</p>

<p>Next one I tried was <a href="http://www.netbeans.org">NetBeans</a>. It has a more slick UI, but more or less it
makes the same mistakes as Eclipse – but worse. :) At least when it comes to
the integration of other languages or tools like Maven. But, and that’s a plus,
it doesn’t feel like patchwork software, when you have lots of plugins
installed. Nevertheless it always felt strange and so I used NetBeans as a mere
editor while using the console to get other things done.</p>

<p>My current IDE instead is JetBrains <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea">IntelliJ</a> (for Java) and <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby">RubyMine</a>
(for Ruby). The one real catch with JetBrains IDEs is that they aren’t free –
there’s a community edition of IntelliJ and free trials for the other ones that
are good for testing. If you’re into open source programming – like me –
you’ll find it useful that JetBrains offers free licenses for open source
projects which is really great. To make it short: JetBrains IDEs are just nice.
They come full-featured for the language they are designed for (IntelliJ is are
more general approach like Eclipse, although it is a Java IDE by design) and
can be extended with lots of plugins. There are (working!) plugins for most of
the common SCMs like Subversion and Git and even more exotic features like
<a href="http://www.freemarker.org">Freemarker</a> support which make JetBrains IDEs really stand out.
Additionally, there are several things that just work in JetBrains IDEs that
gave me a headache in others, e.g. handling of line endings on different
operating systems and code formatting. And I think all those small bits make it
really comfortable to work.</p>

<p>Right now I’m using IntelliJ and RubyMine for the development of
<a href="http://koraktor.github.com/steam-condenser">Steam Condenser</a> and I’m waiting for another open source license for
<a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm">PhpStorm</a> as I’m using a simple editor for the PHP implementation. At the
moment I can’t imagine changing my IDE again as I have never been so
comfortable with one. So as a conclusion I just can recommend JetBrains IDEs.
And no, I’m not paid for this. :)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
